But what we saw is, in the post-9/11 era, they used secrecy and they used the justification of terrorism to start these programs in secret without asking Congress, without asking the American people, and it's that kind of government behind closed doors that we need to guard ourselves against, because it makes us less safe, and it offers no value. CA: Okay, come with me here for a sec, because I've got a more personal question for you. Speaking of terror, most people would find the situation you're in right now in Russia pretty terrifying. You obviously heard what happened, what the treatment that Bradley Manning got, Chelsea Manning as now is, and there was a story in Buzzfeed saying that there are people in the intelligence community who want you dead. How are you coping with this? How are you coping with the fear? ES: It's no mystery that there are governments out there that want to see me dead. I've made clear again and again and again that I go to sleep every morning thinking about what I can do for the American people. I don't want to harm my government. I want to help my government, but the fact that they are willing to completely ignore due process, they're willing to declare guilt without ever seeing a trial, these are things that we need to work against as a society, and say hey, this is not appropriate. We shouldn't be threatening dissidents. We shouldn't be criminalizing journalism. And whatever part I can do to see that end, I'm happy to do despite the risks. CA: So I'd actually like to get some feedback from the audience here, because I know there's widely differing reactions to Edward Snowden. Suppose you had the following two choices, right? You could view what he did as fundamentally a reckless act that has endangered America or you could view it as fundamentally a heroic act that will work towards America and the world's long-term good? Those are the two choices I'll give you. I'm curious to see who's willing to vote with the first of those, that this was a reckless act? There are some hands going up. Some hands going up. It's hard to put your hand up when the man is standing right here, but I see them. ES: I can see you. (Laughter) CA: And who goes with the second choice, the fundamentally heroic act? (Applause) (Cheers) And I think it's true to say that there are a lot of people who didn't show a hand and I think are still thinking this through, because it seems to me that the debate around you doesn't split along traditional political lines. It's not left or right, it's not really about pro-government, libertarian, or not just that. Part of it is almost a generational issue. You're part of a generation that grew up with the Internet, and it seems as if you become offended at almost a visceral level when you see something done that you think will harm the Internet. Is there some truth to that? ES: It is. I think it's very true. This is not a left or right issue. Our basic freedoms, and when I say our, I don't just mean Americans, I mean people around the world, it's not a partisan issue. These are things that all people believe, and it's up to all of us to protect them, and to people who have seen and enjoyed a free and open Internet, it's up to us to preserve that liberty for the next generation to enjoy, and if we don't change things, if we don't stand up to make the changes we need to do to keep the Internet safe, not just for us but for everyone, we're going to lose that, and that would be a tremendous loss, not just for us, but for the world. CA: Well, I have heard similar language recently from the founder of the world wide web, who I actually think is with us, Sir Tim Berners-Lee. Tim, actually, would you like to come up and say, do we have a microphone for Tim? (Applause) Tim, good to see you. Come up there. Which camp are you in, by the way, traitor, hero? I have a theory on this, but -- Tim Berners-Lee: I've given much longer answers to that question, but hero, if I have to make the choice between the two. CA: And Ed, I think you've read the proposal that Sir Tim has talked about about a new Magna Carta to take back the Internet. Is that something that makes sense? ES: Absolutely. I mean, my generation, I grew up not just thinking about the Internet, but I grew up in the Internet, and although I never expected to have the chance to defend it in such a direct and practical manner and to embody it in this unusual, almost avatar manner, I think there's something poetic about the fact that one of the sons of the Internet has actually become close to the Internet as a result of their political expression. And I believe that a Magna Carta for the Internet is exactly what we need. We need to encode our values not just in writing but in the structure of the Internet, and it's something that I hope, I invite everyone in the audience, not just here in Vancouver but around the world, to join and participate in. CA: Do you have a question for Ed? TBL: Well, two questions, a general question — CA: Ed, can you still hear us? ES: Yes, I can hear you. CA: Oh, he's back. TBL: The wiretap on your line got a little interfered with for a moment. (Laughter) ES: It's a little bit of an NSA problem. TBL: So, from the 25 years, stepping back and thinking, what would you think would be the best that we could achieve from all the discussions that we have about the web we want? ES: When we think about in terms of how far we can go, I think that's a question that's really only limited by what we're willing to put into it. I think the Internet that we've enjoyed in the past has been exactly what we as not just a nation but as a people around the world need, and by cooperating, by engaging not just the technical parts of society, but as you said, the users, the people around the world who contribute through the Internet, through social media, who just check the weather, who rely on it every day as a part of their life, to champion that. We'll get not just the Internet we've had, but a better Internet, a better now, something that we can use to build a future that'll be better not just than what we hoped for but anything that we could have imagined. CA: It's 30 years ago that TED was founded, 1984. A lot of the conversation since then has been along the lines that actually George Orwell got it wrong. It's not Big Brother watching us. We, through the power of the web, and transparency, are now watching Big Brother. Your revelations kind of drove a stake through the heart of that rather optimistic view, but you still believe there's a way of doing something about that. And you do too. ES: Right, so there is an argument to be made that the powers of Big Brother have increased enormously. There was a recent legal article at Yale that established something called the Bankston-Soltani Principle, which is that our expectation of privacy is violated when the capabilities of government surveillance have become cheaper by an order of magnitude, and each time that occurs, we need to revisit and rebalance our privacy rights. Now, that hasn't happened since the government's surveillance powers have increased by several orders of magnitude, and that's why we're in the problem that we're in today, but there is still hope, because the power of individuals have also been increased by technology. I am living proof that an individual can go head to head against the most powerful adversaries and the most powerful intelligence agencies around the world and win, and I think that's something that we need to take hope from, and we need to build on to make it accessible not just to technical experts but to ordinary citizens around the world. Journalism is not a crime, communication is not a crime, and we should not be monitored in our everyday activities. CA: I'm not quite sure how you shake the hand of a bot, but I imagine it's, this is the hand right here. TBL: That'll come very soon. ES: Nice to meet you, and I hope my beam looks as nice as my view of you guys does. CA: Thank you, Tim. (Applause) I mean, The New York Times recently called for an amnesty for you. Would you welcome the chance to come back to America? ES: Absolutely. There's really no question, the principles that have been the foundation of this project have been the public interest and the principles that underly the journalistic establishment in the United States and around the world, and I think if the press is now saying, we support this, this is something that needed to happen, that's a powerful argument, but it's not the final argument, and I think that's something that public should decide. But at the same time, the government has hinted that they want some kind of deal, that they want me to compromise the journalists with which I've been working, to come back, and I want to make it very clear that I did not do this to be safe. I did this to do what was right, and I'm not going to stop my work in the public interest just to benefit myself. (Applause) CA: In the meantime, courtesy of the Internet and this technology, you're here, back in North America, not quite the U.S., Canada, in this form. I'm curious, how does that feel? ES: Canada is different than what I expected. It's a lot warmer. (Laughter) CA: At TED, the mission is "ideas worth spreading." If you could encapsulate it in a single idea, what is your idea worth spreading right now at this moment? ES: I would say the last year has been a reminder that democracy may die behind closed doors, but we as individuals are born behind those same closed doors, and we don't have to give up our privacy to have good government. We don't have to give up our liberty to have security. And I think by working together we can have both open government and private lives, and I look forward to working with everyone around the world to see that happen. Thank you very much. CA: Ed, thank you. (Applause)
Pero lo que vimos, en la era post 11-S, es que usaron el secreto y la justificación del terrorismo para empezar estos programas en secreto sin consultar al Congreso, ni al pueblo de EE.UU., y es de ese tipo de gobierno a puertas cerradas del que tenemos que protegernos, porque nos hace menos seguros y no aporta valor. CA: Bien, ven conmigo un segundo, porque tengo una pregunta más personal para hacerte. Hablando del terror, muchas personas consideran tu situación actual en Rusia muy aterrorizante. Seguramente escuchaste lo que pasó, el trato que recibió Bradley Manning, ahora Chelsea Manning, y salió una noticia en Buzzfeed diciendo que hay personas en la comunidad de inteligencia que te quieren muerto. ¿Cómo manejas esto? ¿Cómo manejas el miedo? ES: No es ningún misterio que hay gobiernos que me quieren ver muerto. Lo dejé en claro una y otra vez, que me voy a dormir todas las noches pensando qué puedo hacer por el pueblo de EE.UU. No quiero perjudicar a mi gobierno. Quiero ayudar a mi gobierno, pero el hecho de que quieran ignorar por completo el debido proceso, que quieran declarar culpables sin siquiera un juicio previo, estas son cosas contra las que tenemos que trabajar como sociedad y decir que no es apropiado. No deberíamos amenazar a los disidentes. No deberíamos criminalizar al periodismo. Y lo que sea que pueda hacer para ese fin, lo haré con gusto a pesar de los riesgos. CA: Me gustaría recibir algo de feedback de la audiencia aquí presente, porque sé que hay reacciones muy distintas hacia Edward Snowden. Imaginen que tienen las siguientes 2 opciones. Consideran lo que hizo fundamentalmente como un acto imprudente que puso a EE.UU. en peligro, o lo consideran un acto fundamentalmente heroico que funcionará para EE.UU. y el mundo entero a largo plazo. Esas son las opciones que daré. Me gustaría saber quién vota por la primera opción, la de un acto temerario. Se levantan algunas manos. Algunas manos arriba. Es difícil levantar la mano cuando tienes al hombre ahí enfrente, pero veo algunas. ES: Puedo verlos. (Risas) CA: Y ¿quiénes van por la segunda opción la de un acto heroico? (Aplausos) (Ovación) Creo que es cierto decir que hay muchas personas que no levantaron la mano y creo que todavía lo están pensando, porque me parece que el debate no se divide por las líneas políticas tradicionales. No es izquierda o derecha, no se trata de estar a favor del gobierno, de ser libertario ni nada de eso. En parte es un problema generacional. Uds. son parte de una generación que creció con Internet y parece que se ven ofendidos a un nivel casi visceral si ven algo que creen que puede dañar a Internet. ¿Hay algo de cierto en eso? ES: Sí, creo que es cierto. No se trata de ser de izquierda o derecha. Nuestras libertadas básicas, y cuando digo nuestras, no me refiero solo a los estadounidenses, sino a las personas de todo el mundo, no tiene que ver con un problema partidario. Estas cosas en las que creen todas las personas, y depende de todos nosotros protegerlas, y de las personas que han visto y disfrutado de una Internet libre y gratuita depende de nosotros preservar esa libertad para que la próxima generación pueda disfrutarla, y si no cambiamos las cosas, si no nos paramos para hacer los cambios que hay que hacer para mantener la seguridad en Internet, no solo por nosotros sino por todos, vamos a perderla, y será una pérdida tremenda, para nosotros y para todo el mundo. CA: Bueno, escuché un discurso similar hace poco del fundador de la WWW que creo que está con nosotros, Sir Tim Berners-Lee. Tim, de hecho, quiere decir algo, ¿tenemos un micrófono para Tim? (Aplausos) Tim, qué bueno verte. Ven. ¿En qué bando estás, a propósito, traidor o héroe? Tengo una teoría pero... Tim Berners-Lee: He dado respuestas mucho más largas a esa pregunta, pero héroe, si tuviera que elegir entre las dos. CA: Ed, creo que leíste sobre la propuesta de Sir Tim donde hablaba de hacer una nueva Carta Magna para recuperar Internet. ¿Tiene sentido? ES: Por supuesto. Mi generación y yo crecimos no solo pensando en Internet, sino que crecimos en Internet, y aunque nunca hubiese esperado tener la oportunidad de defenderla de una manera tan directa y práctica y encarnarla de esta manera tan inusual y casi a lo Avatar, creo que hay algo de poético en el hecho que uno de los hijos de Internet se ha vuelto cercano a Internet como resultado de su expresión política. Y creo que la Carta Magna para Internet es justo lo que necesitamos. Necesitamos codificar nuestros valores no solo por escrito sino en la estructura de Internet, es algo que espero y los invito a todos en la audiencia, no solo aquí en Vancouver sino en el mundo entero, a unirse y participar. CA: ¿Tienes una pregunta para Ed? TBL: Bueno, 2 preguntas, una pregunta general. CA: ¿Ed, nos escuchas? ES: Sí, los escucho. CA: Volvió. TBL: Pincharon la línea y hubo una interferencia por un momento. (Risas) ES: Es un problema de la NSA. TBL: Desde los 25 años, volviendo atrás y pensando, ¿qué dirías que es lo mejor que hemos logrado a partir de todas las discusiones que tuvimos sobre la web que queremos? ES: Pensando en términos de qué tan lejos podemos ir, creo que es una pregunta que solo está limitada por lo que queremos poner dentro. Creo que la Internet que disfrutamos en el pasado fue exactamente lo que nosotros como nación y como personas del mundo entero necesitábamos, y cooperando, dedicándonos no solo a las partes técnicas como sociedad, sino, como dijiste tú, los usuarios las personas de todo el mundo que contribuyen a través de Internet, de la redes sociales, los que miran el clima, los que confían en ello como parte de su vida, tenemos que defender eso. Tendremos no solo la Internet que tuvimos, sino una mejor Internet, un mejor presente, algo que podamos usar para construir el futuro que será mejor de lo que esperamos y de lo que jamás hemos imaginado. CA: Hace 30 años que se fundó TED, en 1984. Hubo muchas charlas desde entonces siguiendo el razonamiento de que en realidad George Orwell estaba equivocado. No hay un Gran Hermano que nos mira. Nosotros, gracias al poder de la Web, y la transparencia, estamos mirando al Gran Hermano. De alguna manera, tus revelaciones le dieron una puñalada al corazón de esa mirada más bien optimista, pero todavía crees que hay algo para hacer al respecto. Y tú también. ES: Exacto, se puede argumentar que los poderes del Gran Hermano han aumentado muchísimo. Hace poco salió un artículo legal en Yale que establecía el principio Bankston-Soltani que decía que nuestra expectativa de privacidad es violada cuando las capacidades de vigilancia del gobierno se vuelven más baratas en un orden de magnitud, y cada vez que eso sucede, tenemos que revisar y reequilibrar nuestros derechos de privacidad. Eso no ha sucedido desde que los poderes de vigilancia del gobierno aumentaron en varios órdenes de magnitud, y por eso tenemos el problema que tenemos hoy pero todavía hay esperanza, porque los poderes de los individuos también se incrementaron con la tecnología. Soy una prueba viviente de que un individuo puede ir cabeza a cabeza contra los adversarios más poderosos y las agencias de inteligencia más poderosas del mundo y ganar, y creo que eso es algo que nos da esperanza, y tenemos que construir sobre eso para que sea accesible no solo para los expertos técnicos sino también para los ciudadanos comunes. El periodismo no es un delito, la comunicación no es un delito y no tienen que monitorear nuestras actividades cotidianas. CA: No sé cómo se le da la mano a un bot, pero me imagino que la mano es esta. TBL: Pronto llegará. ES: Un placer conocerte, espero que me vean tan bien como yo los veo a Uds. CA: Gracias, Tim. (Aplausos) El New York Times pidió una amnistía para ti. ¿Aceptarías una oportunidad para volver a EE.UU.? ES: Claro. Sin dudas, los principios que han sido el fundamento de este proyecto han sido el interés público y los principios que subyacen al establishment periodístico de EE.UU. y del mundo, y creo que la prensa ahora dice apoyamos esto, esto es algo que tenía que pasar, es un argumento fuerte pero no es el argumento final, es el público el que debe decidir. Pero al mismo tiempo, el gobierno dio a entender que quiere un tipo de acuerdo, que quieren que comprometa a los periodistas con los que trabajé, a regresar, y quiero dejar en claro que no hice esto para estar a salvo. Hice esto para hacer lo correcto, y no voy a detener mi trabajo en interés del público solo para beneficiarme. (Aplausos) CA: Mientras tanto, por cortesía de Internet y la tecnología, estás de vuelta en América del Norte, no en EE.UU., sino en Canadá. ¿Qué se siente? ES: Canadá es diferente de lo que pensaba. Es mucho más cálido. (Risas) CA: En TED, la misión es "Ideas que vale la pena difundir". Si pudieras encapsular todo en una idea, ¿cuál sería tu idea que vale la pena difundir en este momento? ES: Diría que el año pasado fue un recordatorio de que la democracia puede morir detrás de puertas cerradas, pero los individuos nacemos detrás de esas mismas puertas cerradas, y no tenemos que ceder nuestra privacidad para tener un buen gobierno. No tenemos que ceder nuestra libertad para tener seguridad. Trabajando juntos podemos tener un gobierno honesto y vidas privadas, y espero trabajar con todos en el mundo entero para que esto pase. Muchas gracias. CA: Muchas gracias. (Aplausos)